Hello and welcome back to another
episode with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be looking at phase changes,
specifically how to calculate and
use the heat of vaporization and the
heat of fusion to calculate heat.
So whenever we have a phase change,
what, what are we talking about?
So let's say if I have a solid ice
cube here in the middle, and it's
made of all these little waters,
all oriented in a very crystalline
structure, you can see all the little
solids, all really close together.
Now, as they start absorbing heat,
And start gaining, um, energy
as a result, it will start to
move a little bit farther apart.
The intermolecular forces will
start to drift farther and
farther apart as they gain energy.
And it's going to start
making a liquid as a result.
Now when that happens, right, going
from a solid to a liquid, right, that is
when we're referring to melting, right?
And the opposite is all about freezing.
So when we first melt, right, those
intermolecular forces are really far
apart, it goes through a phase change.
That is when we have to use
the heat of fusion to calculate
that, the numbers behind that.
Now, if that liquid is sitting there
for a long time and it keeps absorbing
energy, eventually what will happen is
a lot of those little water molecules,
they'll eventually break into the gas
phase, making a big gas cloud where all
of them are little, are vapor particles.
Um, that can eventually ricochet and
bounce off the different walls of
the container that they might be in.
And we would have to use the
heat of vaporization to talk
about that phase change.
Which, whenever we are either going
through boiling or vaporization.
That is when it goes
from a liquid to a gas.
So, we are going to be looking at
that and trying to understand that
complete picture in this video.
So, this is for introductory chem,
um, and, and slightly for gen chem
one for a lot of students out there.
But it's just the basics on how to
use delta H and use that with moles
to go through different calculations.
So let's take a look, and if this is
something that's really interesting
to you, please hit that like button.
Sub to the channel and you can see
more videos on topics like these.
All right, let's go into it.
All right, let's start with the
fundamentals, start with the basics.
So let's first review of what I just
said before, which is if you are
having a change of state or or a phase
change, both these words are generally
used interchangeably depending on
who your professor is and who and
where you are learning chemistry.
So, whenever we talk about a phase,
we have a solid, liquid, or a gas.
Same idea as states.
We have a solid, liquid, or a gas.
So if I'm going from a solid to a
liquid, that is whenever if I take an
ice cube and you were to have it in your
hand, what is going to happen to it?
Well, that ice cube is going
to eventually melt, right?
Now if you take your melted water and
stick it back in the freezer, well
that liquid, if you go backwards.
Is going to freeze.
Now, when we have these phase
changes, this is where the heat of
fusion is going to be used, okay,
and we'll go over what formula.
that will be required during that point.
Now when you have the other phase change,
let's say if I go from a liquid to a
gas, meaning that these liquid particles,
these intermolecular forces are going
to drift so far apart that eventually
we're able to break the intermolecular
forces, taking a lot of energy to do that.
This is whenever we have, uh, it's either
it's going to be considered to be boiling
or vaporization to go into the gas phase.
Now, if you were to take those gases,
you were to cool them back down, right?
They have a lot of kinetic energy.
They're moving around very, because
you put so much heat into them.
If you were to cool them back
down, well, that is now going to
be referred to as condensation.
It's the cooling, right?
Bringing it down.
So we, we go through condensation.
If you think of like, uh, if you wake
up really early in the morning when
it's cold outside, you'll see dew on
the grass, on everything that's outside.
This is condensation.
Now when that happens, this is going to be
referred to as the heat of vaporization.
to how to calculate
these different values.
Now when it comes to heat, so usually what
we'll use is the letter Q to denote heat.
Now when it comes to anything
that's energetic related, we have
to realize that there are signs
behind these because there's
endothermic and exothermic processes.
So with this, if you were to
have an ice cube in your hand and
you were to hold it there, Is it
absorbing heat or releasing heat?
And think about it for a second.
Is what's happening to that
ice cube, is it getting hotter?
Well, that means it's yes, right?
It's absorbing heat.
So absorbing is a positive value.
So if you're melting, you're
going to have a positive value.
And if you're boiling, you're
going to have a positive Q value.
Versus, let's say if you want to
freeze it or to condense it, the
ice or the water, whatever phase it
is, needs to lose heat, it needs to
release it in order to get colder.
So whenever we are going into the opposite
process of condensation and freezing, that
is going to be a negative Q value, okay?
So it all depends on whether
or not you are going one way or
the other will reflect what you
will see in your calculation.
Let's take a look at the different
formulas you will be using.
So these are both of them here, so that
for Q, both of these are, depends on
delta H fusion, delta H vaporization,
usually they have a little subscript
that tells you which one you're going
to use, so Q is our heat value when
we are looking at this, N is always
referred to as moles, and And delta H is
something that we call as enthalpy, but
for most intensive purposes it's just
delta H effusion just to keep it a little
easier for most introductory students.
So we're multiplying these two concepts
together in order to calculate our heat.
Let's take a look at some different
examples of the kinds of problems
that you will see and how to solve
for this portion, how to plug in
our different values for this.
Our first example, calculate
the heat when 36 grams of
water is melted at 0 degrees C.
Okay, so how exactly do we do this?
Well, it's going to require us to use
our, our Q equation for a phase change.
So this is going to be N times
delta H, and being that it's
referring to fusion, usually it's
abbreviated as F U S, or fusion,
when we are seeing these equations.
So the first thing you need to do
is we have, what were we given?
We need to stay organized
with these things.
We were given a mass value, which is 36.
0 grams, that is not a mole value.
And we were given a delta H of fusion.
So what exactly do we have to do first?
Well, if you can think of all of
our different calculations when
it comes to masses and moles,
our goal is always the mole.
So the first thing that we need
to do is convert grams to moles.
So, one thing that I did here
is include the values for how
to get to molar mass, right?
And if you need help with molar
mass, refer to my videos on molar
mass and using mole equations.
So, for this one, right, we have
water is what's being used, so we
need to add up one oxygen atom and
two hydrogen atoms to convert this.
So, when we are doing this little
calculation here for ourselves, and
here let's make some room for ourselves.
This is going to be 18 grams for water,
and this is just rounded just to make
it a little easier math on ourselves.
And that's equivalent to
every 1 mole of water.
So that's going to be
equal to 2 moles of H2O.
We have our mole value, and what we're
going to do is we're going to plug
both the delta H of fusion and the mole
value into this equation up here, right?
So we're going to plug both parts in.
So 2 moles is going to go in for N.
And then the 6.
02 kilojoules is going to
go in for delta fusion.
So let's solve.
If we have Q that's going to be times 2.
00 moles times 6.
02 kilojoules per mole.
And what we are going to quickly see
is that moles cancels moles and what
we will be left with is, um, 12.
04 kilojoules for our answer, and we
will round that to the same number as
sig figs that we had in our, in our
original problem, so this would be 12.
0 kilojoules.
Now, is this positive or is it negative?
Well, being that it was melting, it
needed to absorb heat, so this would
stay as a positive value, so 12.
0.
Now the follow up question is,
how much heat is required to
freeze the exact same sample?
So instead of melting it,
how would you freeze it?
Well, think about it.
One way is, it's just all
about the sign changes.
So before, it was a positive 12.
0 kilojoules to melt it, right?
So what would it be in order to freeze it?
Well, it's going to be the opposite.
So it'd be negative 12.
0 kilojoules in order to freeze it.
It's all about how that
delta H's sign changes.
So when it comes to delta H of
fusion for freezing, instead
that would have been a 6.
02, and it's negative
for kilojoules per mole.
Alright, so the sign of our
delta H changes depending on
if it's positive or negative.
Whether we're freezing it or melting it.
Let's go on to our next problem.
To reduce swelling, a 237 gram
ice pack is placed on the body.
How much heat in joules will it
take to melt the ice and warm up
the liquid water to 37 degrees C?
Okay, this is something that
combines different concepts.
So there's another video that was
released at the same time as this
one, which is all about specific heat.
And there was a video released a few
months ago on how to do heat as well.
So this is something that it
requires us to understand how do
these energy diagrams look like.
So at first, it talks about a phase,
it talks about a phase change, right?
We have an ice pack, the ice is melting.
So whenever we have these diagrams, we
got to refer to what the temperatures are.
So in order for something to
freeze, it's at zero degrees C.
So when, in order to convert that,
It is a straight line that you see.
This is referring to the ice pack
melting because it takes so much
energy for those intermolecular forces
to get far enough apart so that way
it can actually become a liquid.
Now afterwards what was happening
is it was heated up to 37 degrees.
So usually what we'll see is,
is a slope referring to heating.
Now, if the slope was going the opposite
direction, that would be cooling.
Now, why do we care about this?
This is because there are, there are
multiple heat equations that work here.
We have what I refer to as Q1 and
Q2, being that we're going to be
doing two separate equations here.
So now, why do we care?
It's because we want to stay organized.
So Q1 is what we just did in
our previous problem, right?
N times delta H fusion.
Because it's all about how is this
ice cube melting in your ice pack.
Q2 is all about the MCAT equation, right?
Um, so it's MC delta T.
Something else that's covered
in this type of chapter.
And what we are trying to do is we're
trying to figure out what the total
heat that is required to cool this down.
So in order to do the very last
part, to find the Q total, we
gotta add up Q one plus Q two
in order to get our final value.
So we got to do a little bit of
work here, but let's first take
a look at what we did last time.
So the first thing we
need is our mass, right?
It was 237 grams is what is
being given to us in the problem.
237 grams of water to be exact.
So when we go through that, we
need to convert that to moles in
order to use our first equation.
So 237 grams of water.
In order to convert that to moles,
we have to once again use our
molar mass, which is 18 grams of
water is equivalent to one mole.
of water.
Grams cancels grams, and what we
are going to get is once we do 237
divided by 18, we are going to get
about, and after rounding, is 13.
2 moles of water.
Okay, now what we can do is with
that value is plug it in to our
equation from earlier, so that 13.
2 moles can get plugged in for n.
And being that I, that we have the
delta H value as well, which was 6.
02 times, uh, 6.
02 kilojoules, that can get
plugged in for delta H effusion.
So let's solve Q1.
So Q1 is, after getting
all of our values, is 13.
2 moles times 6.
02 kilojoules for every mole.
We can now see that the
moles will cancel moles.
So that's another thing, you can
always let the units kind of guide
your thinking and your process here.
Um, and what we will have after
doing the math is about, um, 79.
5 kilojoules for Q1.
Q2.
So Q2 is using the MCAT equation.
So what exactly is happening here?
Well, we have our mass, right?
That's a 237.
What about delta T?
So delta T, for those of you
who might not realize, that is
the TF, so final minus initial.
Now what was our initial value?
Well, looking at our curve, that
was about 0 degrees Celsius.
And end it at about 37 degrees C.
So this is our TF and our TI in our
original equations that we have here.
So this is why we want to make sure
we're organized, labeling what we have,
so that way we can see, all right,
what exactly is going to be happening.
So let's kind of write down our Q2 here.
So this is MC delta T.
M was 237 grams, uh, delta T is going
to be final, which is 37 degrees C,
minus 0 degrees C, which is just 37
degrees C, um, once we subtract those,
and then our C value is another value
that is given to us, which is 4.
186 joules over grams times Celsius.
We have all the parts.
Let's plug it in.
Once we do that, we have our 237 grams.
We're going to multiply
that times our C value.
Then we're going to multiply that
times our change in temperature.
And what we are going to end up
getting for Q, for this Q value,
is being that this is in joules,
this is going to be 36, 707 joules.
Now, can I just add the
two values together?
Well, if you notice from
Q1, this is in kilojoules.
Q2 is in joules.
So what do we have to do is we have
to convert them to the same unit.
So, it's pretty easy to convert
to kilojoules, so maybe we'll
just do that real quick.
So if we divide 36, 707 by
1000, that will give you your
joules, uh, sorry, kilojoules.
So that will be 36.
7 kilojoules for one number, and then
we have the other one from earlier.
Let's now add them together.
So Qtotal.
It's going to be 36.
7 kilojoules plus our 79.
5 kilojoules from earlier.
This was Q2 and Q1.
So in the very end, what
you will get is 116.
2 kilojoules of total energy that's
required to melt an ice pack and to heat
an ice pack from zero to 37 degrees.
So these heat of fusion, heat
of vaporization problems can
get a little involved and they
can involve a lot of steps.
So if you have a multi step heating
and cooling and phase change, you've
got to add up every single part.
I hope this video helped you
try to learn a little bit more
about fusion vaporization, going
through the problem walkthroughs.
More videos to come.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button if it has been helping you and
thank you so much for your support.
Please let me know what you
thought down below and I hope to
see you around for future videos.
Bye now.